Guide to the Spanish Civil War Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Spanish Civil War Collection
1936-2011
MS 2058
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.83
(4 boxes)
The collection documents society and events during the Spanish Civil War. Formats include magazines and comic books, handbills, pamphlets, broadsides, manuscripts, and toys. Both Nationalist and Republican perspectives are represented in the materials. Materials date between 1936-2011, with the bulk between 1936-1943.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Latin American Collection Curator, 2016-2019.
Arrangement
The material is arranged by accession and by document type.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents society and events during the Spanish Civil War. Formats include magazines and comic books, handbills, pamphlets, broadsides, manuscripts, and toys. Both Nationalist and Republican perspectives are represented in the materials. Materials date between 1936-2011, with the bulk between 1936-1943.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939; Franco, Francisco, 1892-1975; Falange Española de las J.O.N.S
- Inventory
  - Children's magazines, 1937-1943
    - Maravillas, 1939-10-05-1939-11-30; 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      A supplement comic to "Flechas y Pelayos". "Maravillas", along with "Flechas y Pelayos", was the most characteristic child and adolescent publication of Franco during the 1940s. The magazine was published in San Sebastian by the National Delegation of the Youth Front and was led by Justo Pérez de Urbel. It began publication in 1939 and ran for 640 issues. The title carried the subtitle Año de la Victoria. Includes six issues: numbers 8, 10, 12-13, 15-16.
    - Almanaque: Mis chicas, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      "Mis Chicas" was a Spanish comic book published in San Sebastian between 1941 and 1950 by Consuelo Gil. It had 407 issues and was the first women's magazine in the Spanish war and for many years the only one. It was aimed at girls older than seven, although their mean age was significantly higher, with some readers in their twenties. It also aimed to capture their brothers as readers. It included various sections: film, literature, morality, and Letter of Aunt Catherine (dedicated to contact readers), plus novels, such as Marisa Villardefrancos. The cartoons were less political and focused on traditional feminine values: beauty, charity, kitchen, maternity, etc. Includes one issue.
    - YO: Semanario infantil, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3-3a)
      Complete run of YO (41 issues), a Republican childrens comic published in Barcelona from 1937-1938. It was cancelled after 41 issues as the war closed in on Barcelona. As the war proceeded, stories about the war began appearing in the comics. Some stories were overtly about the struggle while other strips, such as "Aventuras del Rey Feliz" and "Beba Usted un Poco Más", were a more subtle swipe at the fascists.
  - International brigades, 1937-2011
    - Las brigadas internacionales según testimonios de sus artífices, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Published by the Comité de Informacíon y Actuación Social (CIAS), and illustrated throughout. The CIAS attempted to prove that the International Brigades were organized, orchestrated, and directed by the Russian Communist party, with many quotations from contemporary publications and statements by politicians and participants, as well as reproductions of propaganda pieces (e.g. posters and magazines).
    - The Story of the Abraham Lincoln Battalion: Written in the Trenches of Spain, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - I am an International: Nate Thornton's Story, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs and postcards, 1936-1939; 2
    - Spanish refugees on the French border postcards, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Set of twelve photographic postcards from the Cliché Studio Chauvin in Perignan regarding the refugee crisis on the French border during the Spanish Civil War. Includes a photograph of a large sign for FRANCO, giving refugees a choice of whether to stay in Spain or enter France. Incomplete set.
    - Press photographs, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Two press photographs from the Spanish Civil War. Paris, London: Photos NYT, Keystone View Company, 1936, with dittoed agency notes pasted to reverse. One photograph (9.5 inches by 7.5 inches) depicts "Xmas dinner on the Spanish War Front, picture by air from our own correspondent," or government soldiers on the Valdemero-Pinto section of the Madrid front eating Christmas dinner, and is dated 1936 December 28. A second photograph (7 inches x 5 inches) depicts a man with a gun standing by a bombed-out building, with caption on the back reading "Les dégâts causés à une maison de Geusa (Aragon) par une grenade bombe de l'artillerie nationale," and is dated 1936 October 20.
  - Broadsides, 1937-1938
    - La ficha de refugiados, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Ministerio de Sanidad y Asistencia Social; Oficina Central de Ecacuación y Asistencia a Regufiados. Delegación de Albacete. Handbill. Albacete: La Oficina, 1930s. Flyer intended to give hope to refugees from fascism; includes the address of the office dedicated to assisting them.
    - ¡Noticia sensacional!, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Madrid: Ateneo Libertario de Cuatro Caminos [1937]. Announces a public address by Joaquin Cortés, Miguel González Inestral, Federica Montseny and J. García Pradas to discuss the Iberian Anarchist Federations' new structure as adopted the previous month in Valencia.
    - Para detener a los traidores..., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Para detender a los traidores de España y a los ejércitos de Hitler y Musolini... Published by La Comisión de Reclutamiento de los Batallones de Obras y Fortificaciones - C.N.T.-U.G.T.
    - Au monde civilisé..., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Au monde civilisé de prononcer son jugement!
    - Orden: Actuación de personal, 1938-09-02 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Jefatura Central de Trasportes del Ministerio de Hacienda y Economía, Madrid. Main body of text is a reminder of the duties of personnel who have been assigned vehicles, emphasizing how valuable a vehicle is during times of war. Cites Juan Vila Moragas, who protected the vehicle he had been assigned from two armed assailants. He slammed his door into one of them, and remained to suervise the car, even after the assailants shot him and fled. Below this is a section listing four less honorable personnel who have been arrested and given sentences ranging from five days to one month for various derelictions.
    - Al pueblo de Vallecas, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Two handbills with the same title but different content. Vallecas, Madrid: Partido Comunista. One urges communists, socialists, anarchists and other Republicans to united in the Popular Front. The other urges recipients to join the DECA (Republican Special Aircraft Defence)
    - Estado Nacional Sindicalista: Puntos iniciales, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      One broadside, 54 cm x 39 cm.
  - Collection of documents from the Cículo Español Socialista in Havana, Cuba, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Sixteen letters related to supporting the Republican cause in Spain. Subjects include: floating a bond sale, buying an ambulance, sending materials to Spain, non-payment of goods, propaganda for the bond sale, money management, and various letters on other subjects. All documents are signed by the Secretary or President of their time. Includes letters sent to Josée Nuñez. Other correspondents include Manuel Palacio, Aveline Rodriguez, Jose Otero, Jesus Lopez Lombera, and Jacinto del Peso. Also includes one document from the Spanish Embassy in Havana on the submission of cigarettes for the Republican Army in Spain, 1938 May 31, signed by Carlos Montilla.
  - Aerial bombing record, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Manuscript record of an aerial bombing by the 120th Squadron of the Italian Aviazione Legionaria, 1937 August 6-28. The names of each pilot are shown with where they conducted operations. It is signed by the commander of the Squadron Group and by the commander of the Squadron. The manuscript is in red ink, indicating that all flights occurred at night.
  - A Fugitive from Spain, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Extracts translated into Engish from a lecture given in Lima, Peru. Originally published in Spanish in the newspaper "El Comerio de Lima", 1936 November 8-9. Published by the Spanish Relief Committee, San Francisco, California.
  - Unificación por "El Fugitivo", 1938 June (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Propaganda booklet published by Falange Españoa Tradicionalista y de las J.O.N.S. Colored illustrations and artwork by Teodoro Delgado.
  - Ration coupons, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Seven sheets of apparent food ration coupons issued in Spain during the Civil War. However, due to the fact that both sides of the conflict are represented and the incompatibility of the artistic quality with the notion of rationing, these appear to be fantasy pieces. Shown are both Republican (including the Abraham Lincoln Brigade) and Falangist images, as well as images of many towns and regions of Spain.
  - Revista para la mujer, 1938-06 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Published by La Sección Feminina de Falange Española Tradicionalista y de los J.O.N.S. Early publication from the "liberated" city of San Sebastian addressed to the woman of Spain. The lead article is about what the Nationalist wife should do while her husband has risen the Army. Includes numerous articles on Catholicism; fashion; the history of the Falangist Feminine Section by Pilar Primo de Rivera, sister of the founder of the Falange movements; notes on books; and the Italian life of Mussolini.
  - Comunismo en España (1919-1936), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Comin Colomer, Eduardo. El Comunismo en España (1919-1936). Madird: Publicaciones Españolas, 1953. Part of Temas Españolas, no. 49.
  - Auxilio Social, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes one item.
  - Arriba España flipbook, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Early 1940s flipbook showing Franco giving the fascist salute.
  - Manuscript diary of a Falangist girl, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Manuscript diary of an unnamed Falangist girl, 1938-1940. She was apparently the daughter of a military officer or consul, as there are many references to her visits to consultates as well as several references to senior military offers visiting her home for dinner. The majority of the entries were written in Zaragoza, with other entries throughout Spain.
  - Republican child's game board, 1940-1955; 1; folder (Broadside) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Children's Republican board game, approximately 45 cm x 45 cm, titled "Muy Heroica Ciudad de Madrid 1936-1939". The game features allegories representing two socialist trade unions (Uníon General de Trabajadores and the Confederación National del Trabajo), as well as two left wing parties (Izquierda Republicana and Partido Comunista), with the seal of the city of Madrid in the middle.
- Additional materials, 1936-2011; Accession 2018-m-0021
  - Reconnaissance flight log, 1937-07-16-1937-10-25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Flight log of Sergeant Armando Tarabini, Aviazione Legionaria, signed and stamped by his commanders. Tarabini mainly flies alone, generally policing an area, but, at times, flies with Captain Antonio Rinaldo when he is transporting materials or doing reconnaisance.
  - Falangist children's coloring book, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Coloring book with artwork by Laokin, a Falange artist. The theme of the coloring book is the triumph of the Falange over the Republic.
  - Memorial poster to fallen soldier, 1940? (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Portrait memorial to Luciano Manrique Cimeno, nationalist soldier who died on 1938 July 30.
- Additional materials, 1937-1945; Accession 2019-M-0042
  The accession includes children's materials, publications, and postcards documenting the Spanish Civil War.
  - Children's materials, 1937-1945
    Includes children's magazines, books, and drawings.
    - El mes petit de tots, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Republican children's book published by the Comissariat de Propaganda de la Generalitat de Catalunya in 1937.
    - Almanaque Mis Chicas, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Almanaque Chicos, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      This magazine began in San Sebastian with no editor, under the edition of the industrial Joan Baygual i Bas, who was also linked to the Carlist newspaper El Correo Catalan and contributed to the financing of Pelayos, edited by the National Carlist Board. In November 1938, Chicos was seized by the National Press and Propaganda Delegation of FET and the Jon. It ran from 1938-1950 and began with the subtitle "the year of victory"; this subtitle was abandoned in 1942. The almanacs ran from 1941-1950.
    - Children's drawings about the war, 1944- (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Five original drawings by an unidentified child about the Spanish Civil War. The drawings demonstrate the child's support of the Nationalist cause.
  - La conversion de los ninos en rufianes: la nueva educacion Nazi, 1939? (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Republican booklet titled "The Conversion of Children into Ruffians: The New Nazi Education," regarding fascism and German youth.
  - Historia de tres dias, 1940? (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Piece by Jose Maria Peman regarding the historic entry into Madrid.
  - Propaganda postcards, 1937? (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Twelve postcards published by the Catalunya Comissariat de Propaganda. Includes captions, in four languages, on the back of each card.
  - Partes officiales de guerra: nacionales y rojos, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes printed radio scripts that aired from July to December 1936.
  - La Revista de la Mujer Nacional Sindicalista, 1938 February (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Magazine devoted to motherhood and Falange women. This is the first issue, dated February 1938.